<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Euro Code(x)</title><link href="http://mjvw.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://mjvw.github.io/feeds/non-academic.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://mjvw.github.io/</id><updated>2017-03-18T23:55:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>C’est quoi, être Néerlandais?</title><link href="http://mjvw.github.io/dutchness.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-18T23:55:00+01:00</published><author><name>mjvw</name></author><id>tag:mjvw.github.io,2017-03-18:dutchness.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;What makes the Dutch, Dutch? A constitutional perspective.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since the rise of the Christian Democrats in the beginning of the 2000's, the issue of &lt;em&gt;'Normen en Waarden'&lt;/em&gt; has been a topic in the elections. The &lt;em&gt;CDA&lt;/em&gt; is widely seen to have won the first of a line of elections under the leadership of Balkenende by framing the problems in Dutch society as the result of individualistic attitudes, propagated by the preceding cabinets. As with a lot of electoral rethoric, there was no real explanation on what that meant, but the answer was a return to &lt;a href="&amp;quot;http://dnpp.ub.rug.nl/dnpp/pp/cda/jv/2002&amp;quot; Dutch"&gt;Dutch Values (&lt;em&gt;Normen en Waarden&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;. A standard question in interviews and election debates has since been: "Dear party leader, what do you see as Dutch Values?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For citizens of a number of different countries, the allusion is clear. &lt;em&gt;Normen en Waarden&lt;/em&gt; is identity politics in its most embryonic form. An American would translate a question on American Values into a response on what it means to be American. Since the days of Big Society, most British citizens would equally start giving a vision on &lt;a href="http://press.conservatives.com/post/151242631480/johnson-how-british-values-help-to-make-the-world"&gt;Britishness&lt;/a&gt;. Still, it is only after 17 years that a political leader has dared to follow the Values debate to its logical conclusion. Shockingly, it wasn't Geert Wilders who opened that door. Rather, it was the leader of the same party that brought us &lt;em&gt;'Normen en Waarden'&lt;/em&gt; who started talking about Dutchness. Although the media have smirked at his proposals for Dutch children to stand to attention and sing the national anthem with hand to heart, it has remained a talking point in this election cycle. So let's explore the Dutch identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why is discussing Dutchness so difficult?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would probably be an interesting book proposal to have writers discuss the Dutch identity through anecdotes. To offer a small insight, no Dutch national in my department would even think about describing his or herself as 'Dutch'. There is, outside of football, no such thing as 'proudly Dutch'. My favourite description remains: "Being Dutch means that your practical approach to life and politics leads you to dismiss idiotic questions such as 'What does it mean to be Dutch?'" The question rises: "Why is it so difficult to discuss Dutch identity?". As a legal scholar, I would like to propose a constitutionalist view on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us accept that most national identities are merely social constructs. A way to differentiate 'us' from 'them'. There are many ways in which this can be done. Lawyers will be aware of the language laws that tried to forge a French and German identity. One of the most prominent ways in which identity is formed is through an (implicit) social contract. I'll leave discussion on shared history to those better equipped to discuss that point. But let us take a legalistic view. The jewish people are probably one of the oldest examples. They have a contract with God, giving laws and binding them as a (his) people. The American Constitution is a similar contract, only between the people themselves, "We, the people {...}". Although history has made it problematic for Germans to approach national pride in the same way, the position of the Constitutional Court and the freedoms protected by the German Constitution are clearly regarded as unassailable. Conversely, when the discussion on identity falter, we equally see a reliance on these contracts in an attempt to secure unity. The Catalan people are kept into greater Spain through reliance on &lt;a href="http://www.iconnectblog.com/?s=catalan+independence"&gt;clauses in the Constitution&lt;/a&gt;. In the 'Better Together' campaign in the UK, the history of the Act of Union surfaced multiple times. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Constitutions are, amongst all the other things that they can be, the testament of one singular moment in which a people have declared that they are one. They do so by declaring what values they share. To put it a bit more honestly, constitutions tell the story of why you are better than all your neighbours, who are therefore NOT part of your club. The Netherlands have had plenty of moments which could have given rise to a strong national identity. We have fought, and won, a 80 years long war against a superior aggressor. During that war of indepence, we built towards our Golden Age. We early on became a nation so open to ideas and enterprise, that we could command a sum of money that vastly outstripped our territorial value to build &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b071vl2l"&gt;a vast trading empire&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps our greatest claim to fame, the British hated us. Yet there was never an explicit moment in which 'The Dutch' laid down what they were. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nrc.nl/nieuws/2016/09/09/onze-identiteit-volgens-den-haag-4215563-a1520694"&gt;Recently&lt;/a&gt;, the leader of the Christian Democrats referred to the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Act_of_Abjuration"&gt;'Plakkaat van Verlatinghe'&lt;/a&gt;, our Declaration of Independence. This is true, but although Americans are proud of the Declaration, it is the Constitution that they cite as the proof that America is the greatest country on earth. Conversely, the &lt;em&gt;Plakkaat&lt;/em&gt; is very pratical in its declaration and reason to secede from the Spanish crown. The more recent Dutch attempts of constitutionalism have similar problems. After a succesful period as one of the first republics in history, the end of the Napoleonic era brought a fear in the Dutch well-to-do and nobility that we needed to have a monarchy to secure stability. There was no 'national moment' behind the introduction of the monarchy, if anything that identity was forged after Willem I was put into place. The constitutions from 1815 until 1848 reflect this practical approach. They deal with organising the state, the relationship between King and Parliament, and a very short rights catalogue. Where the other nations of Europe were in the throws of revolution, identity shaping events, we were going the other way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Constitutionality, now!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value of the constitution remains ambiguous to this day. It is not a social contract amongst the Dutch. The values that lie therein are of a practical nature, all can be moderated and limited as it suits the situation. Dutch children are rarely taught what constitutional values mean. And why should they? As the Dutch courts are prohibited from testing laws against the constitution. There is no possibility for constitutional review. All discussions on this point are, in a very Dutch and practical manner, waved away. Dutch courts can make use of international treaties to test acts by government, thereby securing rights. But that means that courts are implementing &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; values, not Dutch ones. Nor is there a Constitutional Court which can pronounce on what Dutch constitutional values are. From the perspective of the constitutionalist, it isn't possible to say what it means to be Dutch, because the Dutch have never take the time to write it down. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this matter in the current electoral debate? On the one hand, the debate on Dutch identity has never really bothered citizens to a great extent, the ambiguity suits them. To most voters, the discussion will therefore remain a purely hypothetical one. I would dare say that even if &lt;em&gt;CDA&lt;/em&gt; forces the point of mandatory anthem singing, most people will just not do it. On the other hand, the rise of populism has made it clear that there are some problems with the Dutch system. We say that we hold certain values dear, but there is no way in which to enforce them. A populist majority can implement discriminatory laws without engaging with the constitution. If judges oppose them, international regimes will be blamed, an occurence all to familiar in the UK at the moment. It has been said that the Netherlands has been a country that from the Golden Age has benefitted from open borders, for people, ideas and money, but this isn't reflected in any (judicially enforceable) system. Dutch children are told that racism and discrimination are prohibited, but if we need to tell them why, there isn't an easy document to which we can point. "Yes it is also in the constitution, but that doesn't really matter. However, please have a look at these bylaws that implement international agreements." If the German constitutional experience has taught us anything, than it is that constitutional identity does not need to come through centuries of culture. If the Netherlands want to know what it means to be Dutch, they should try and write it down. Until that day, the political discussion is as vague as it is useless.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="politics"></category><category term="identity"></category><category term="culture"></category><category term="constitutional identity"></category><category term="Albrecht Sonntag"></category><category term="Ideas on Europe"></category><category term="blogs"></category></entry><entry><title>Contribution to Mails d'Europe</title><link href="http://mjvw.github.io/where_is_the_left.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-08T11:19:00+01:00</published><author><name>mjvw</name></author><id>tag:mjvw.github.io,2017-03-08:where_is_the_left.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.essca.fr/EU-Asia/people/albrecht-sonntag/"&gt;Professor Albrecht Sonntag&lt;/a&gt; has a very interesting idea of a series of blogs on the elections that seem to be so important for the future of Europe. Through both his blog at &lt;a href="https://www.essca.fr/EU-Asia/"&gt;ESSCA&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://allianceeuropa.ideasoneurope.eu/"&gt;Ideas on Europe -blog&lt;/a&gt;, he has asked academics throughout Europe to mail him their responses to, as he calls them, his stupid French questions. The idea is wonderful. We cannot possibly know the intricacies that haunt each election. By accepting our naivite, and by daring to ask the 'stupid questions' to our friends abroad, we gain a greater understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have greatly enjoyed the contributions by the other authors, and I encourage everyone to keep an eye out for these blogs. Furthermore, the collaboration with professor Sonntag, sparring about the problems in our respective countries, has been a joy. I would like to thank him again for his help, his edits, and the great visuals he has added to my piece. You should have a look for the edited and improved version that has been published &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/IdeasOnEurope"&gt;on his blog&lt;/a&gt;. For this personal blog, I have made use of my original submission.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What ever happened to the left?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions on the vital statistics of 'The Left' are rising everywhere in the Western World. At least in the Netherlands, it is too early to organise a wake. We may be well known for our liberal and permissive attitude to society (which is not the same as being tolerant, and is more marketing than truth), The Netherlands has never truly had a left wing revolution, silent or otherwise. In part due to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polder_model"&gt;&lt;em&gt;verzuiling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a Dutch form of mild sectarianism along religious and class lines, sometimes called pillarisation) and the closely related &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polder_model"&gt;&lt;em&gt;poldermodel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a system of highly proceduralised consensus-building in government), the welfare state and the economy have always been pragmatically constructed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it had been a long time since the days of &lt;em&gt;verzuiling&lt;/em&gt;, the political spectrum had not meandered far from that structure. Any changes that occurred since the 80's have by-and-large been within the well-known system. New parties would form, but they would adhere to left-right spectrum (and until the 80's, the pillars). In fact, the most significant upstart that advocated system-change, D66, has quickly been encapsulated into the spectrum as the epitome of the middle of the road party. D66 is perhaps the most vivid example of the stolid Dutch political establishment that is reluctant to accept change it cannot qualify. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pillars Toppled&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That ended with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pim_Fortuyn"&gt;Pim Fortuyn&lt;/a&gt;. A politician that now has an almost saint-like status in Dutch culture as the man who dared to speak out against the The Hague apparatchik. The governments before him had been very successful in fostering economic, social, environmental and cultural progress. The so-called Purple Cabinets (&lt;em&gt;Paars I and II&lt;/em&gt;) were a mix of liberal and socialist parties, coming together to form progressive-centrist policies. None of the opposition parties could offer any real resistance. How could they? Purple policies were progressive enough for the liberals, social enough for the reds and in the time of secular liberalism, the Christian parties were out. Pim Fortuyn was the first person to find the cracks in this structure. Due to a rise of immigrants from the Middle East; guest workers brought in after WWII that weren't integrated into society; and the political elite that was enjoying its success too much, a perfect storm was formed. Thus, Fortuyn created a platform for the angry. His party (the LPF) couldn't be qualified along the lines of Dutch politics. It was right-wing in foreign and migration policies, but with redistributive policies only seen in the most socialist of programmes. Combined with the promise to let 'people who had business experience' run the government, it was the first succesful anti-establishment party. For 'The People', not just a pillar as with the socialist movement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 2001 onward, the traditional left-right divide started to fail as an analytical tool or even a useful form of expression. Yet, the system has never recovered from the idea that parties could exist outside of the &lt;em&gt;status quo&lt;/em&gt;. In the wake of the rise and fall of the LPF, a number of contenders has risen, each with a mix of left-wing and right-wing policies. This is best exemplified by the successor of Pim Fortuyn, Geert Wilders and his Freedom Party (PVV). With an agenda filled with xenophobic screed and anti-elite policies, the well-spoken former liberal (a scion of former VVD parlementarian and EU Commissioner Bolkestein) torments both the liberal VVD, and the socialist SP and PvdA. These traditional parties are trying to adapt, incorporating stances heretofore unagreeable to them. The VVD becoming more repressive on law and order, the SP going back to its reactionary socialist roots, and the PvdA has yet to find a response. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Political Spectrum" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/578082/Pictures/axis.jpg" title="An Axis created by quality newspaper 'Trouw' showing the fluidity of Dutch political parties" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So what has happened to 'The Left'?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is that before Fortuyn the old system had led to the adoption of norms in all political parties that would be called 'Left Wing' in other countries. The large losses of the Socialist parties is largely due to the fact that they have not been able to find a new cause after most of their policies had been enacted by the 80's. Even the Christian Democrats advocate a highly organised welfare state, and with &lt;em&gt;ChristenUnie&lt;/em&gt; there is even a (moderate) progressive faction. When the old system of Left-Right politics worked, coalitions would be created along familiar lines, even though that sometimes appeared arbitrary. With the crash of that old system of politics, there is no logical flag to rally round for opposition to Wilders and other populists, even though more values are shared. But in effect, almost all other parties condemn the PVV. And although the PVV is ahead in the polls, so are &lt;em&gt;GroenLinks&lt;/em&gt; (Green Party with a liberal streak) and D66 (Progressive Liberals), polar opposites of Wilders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Left isn't dead. In the Netherlands, without ever really coming into power a lot of the traditionally left wing policies have become an integral part of the political culture. Even with the dissolution of the traditional demarkations by Fortuyn and Wilders, progressive and socialist thought and culture is everywhere in varying degrees. It just can't be pinned down in old taxonomy. The current anger at the so-called "Progressive Left Wing Elite" is therefore mostly a construct of the populists for people to rage against, based on the old convention of the well-to-do city dwellers that would vote Social Democrats, rather than something that actually exists. A more interesting set of questions in The Netherlands is therefore: How do we organise our system after the death of the Left-Right spectrum? Will &lt;em&gt;verzuiling&lt;/em&gt; turn into sectarianism and identity politics?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="politics"></category><category term="left-right"></category><category term="Albrecht Sonntag"></category><category term="Ideas on Europe"></category><category term="blogs"></category></entry><entry><title>Eligible for a Prize</title><link href="http://mjvw.github.io/jcer-prize.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-23T23:30:00+01:00</published><author><name>mjvw</name></author><id>tag:mjvw.github.io,2017-02-23:jcer-prize.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year I finally got around to getting an article published that dealt with the true substance of my PhD research. Given the amount of case law that is being generated at the moment, and the increase in lobbying activity on this point, I wanted to plant my flag. It is not the most charming part of academia, but it is part of the game. It was a great experience, and I highly recommend the journal both for its contributions as its editorial policies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article can be found &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/LimitsToInterpretativeSpace" title="JCER, Open Access"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and I am glad to report that it has been put forward as an potential candidate for the Luke Foster prize. The final decision is down to a vote. Although I am not a great lover of these online popularity contests, I would love for anyone to read the publication, of which I am very proud, and make an informed decision to support me. For what it's worth, all my winnings will go towards the publication of my PhD thesis and probably one celebratory bottle of champagne. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can vote for my article with &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/jcerprize" title="Luke Foster Prize"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;. And be sure to subscribe to the JCER newsletter so you can keep up to date with the interesting things being published there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Matthijs&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="non-academic"></category><category term="prize"></category><category term="article"></category><category term="jcer"></category><category term="phd"></category></entry></feed>