<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Euro Code(x)</title><link href="http://mjvw.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://mjvw.github.io/feeds/non-academic.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://mjvw.github.io/</id><updated>2017-02-23T23:30:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Eligible for a Prize</title><link href="http://mjvw.github.io/jcer-prize.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-23T23:30:00+01:00</published><author><name>mjvw</name></author><id>tag:mjvw.github.io,2017-02-23:jcer-prize.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year I finally got around to getting an article published that dealt with the true substance of my PhD research. Given the amount of case law that is being generated at the moment, and the increase in lobbying activity on this point, I wanted to plant my flag. It is not the most charming part of academia, but it is part of the game. It was a great experience, and I highly recommend the journal both for its contributions as its editorial policies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article can be found &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/LimitsToInterpretativeSpace" title="JCER, Open Access"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and I am glad to report that it has been put forward as an potential candidate for the Luke Foster prize. The final decision is down to a vote. Although I am not a great lover of these online popularity contests, I would love for anyone to read the publication, of which I am very proud, and make an informed decision to support me. For what it's worth, all my winnings will go towards the publication of my PhD thesis and probably one celebratory bottle of champagne. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can vote for my article with &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/jcerprize" title="Luke Foster Prize"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;. And be sure to subscribe to the JCER newsletter so you can keep up to date with the interesting things being published there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Matthijs&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="non-academic"></category><category term="prize"></category><category term="article"></category><category term="jcer"></category><category term="phd"></category></entry></feed>